<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd'>
<book>
   <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <section>
         <title>Motivation</title>
         <para>
            Gwyddion is a modular programme for SPM data analysis. Primarily it is 
            supposed to be used for analysis of height fields obtained by means
            of scanning probe microscopy techniques (AFM, MFM, STM, NSOM), but
            generally it can be used for any other height field analysis or image analysis. 
            Gwyddion is a free software, covered by Gnu General Public License (Gnu GPL).
         </para>
         <para>
            The main idea behind Gwyddion developement is to provide modular programme
            for 2D data analysis that could be easily extended by modules and plugins
            with no need of core recompilation. Moreover, the status of free software
            enables to provide source codes to developers and users, which makes the further
            programme improvement easier.
         </para>
         <para>
            Gwyddion core developement is currently funded by Czech Metrology Institute (www.cmi.cz).
            However, it is supposed that more persons and institutions will participate on developement. 
            Project is open for anyone. 
         </para>
       </section>
      <section>
         <title>Licensing</title>
         <para>
            Gwyddion is covered by Gnu General Public License (Gnu GPL). Netroufam si to popisovat...   
         </para> 
      </section>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Installing Gwyddion</title>
      <para>
          Gwyddion source code and binaries can be downloaded from the web pages of the project
          (http://gwyddion.net). The instalation sligtly varies depending on the operating system used.
          However, basically it consist of two steps:
          <itemizedlist>
             <listitem>
                <para>Installing the Gtk+ enviroment (if not allready done).</para>
             </listitem>
             <listitem>
                <para>Installing Gwyddion</para>
             </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
           The first step is necessary namely on operating systems other than Linux at first Gwyddion installation.
      </para>
      <section>
         <title>Linux version</title>
         <para>
            You can use RPMs or source tarballs as Gwyddion installation source. Then, install the RPM or compile
            and install programme in a usual way.
         </para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Windows version</title>
         <para>
            Download the Gtk+ runtime enviroment and install it (e. g. from http://www.dropline.net/gtk/download.php). 
            Download Gwyddion installator and install Gwyddion. You should need no more steps for Gwyddion runtime installation.
         </para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Linux version for developers</title>
         <para>
            Use source tarballs as Gwyddion installation source. Compile
            and install programme in a usual way. 
         </para>
       </section>
      <section>
         <title>Windows version for developers</title>
         <para>
            If you want to become developer, you can also use Microsoft Visual C++ compiler to compile the application. 
            Use source tarball in that case
            and compile application using Nmake command. In this case you will need Gtk development enviromet installed on your system.
            You can download this enviroment from http://www.dropline.net/gtk/download.php.
            You will probably need to change paths to Gtk+ and MSVC toplevel directories in the make.msc file.
            The default paths are (see first few lines of make.msc):
            <programlisting>
               # XXX: set following to your Gtk+-Development and MSVC paths
               GTK_TOP = C:\Dev-C++
               MSC_TOP = C:\Program Files\Microsoft Visual Studio\VC98
            </programlisting>
         </para>
 
      </section>
    </section>
   <section>
      <title>Getting started</title>
      <section>
         <title>Managing files</title>
         <para>
            Gwyddion uses its internal data format (.gwy) to store data. The main advantage of this format is fact, that it stores
            complete state of processing of concrete data, including selections and other tool and processing
            fucntion settings. Therefore we recommned to use this format for saving processed files.
         </para>
         <para>
            Other data file formats can be handled with appropriate loading and saving modules or plugins. Currently, only simple
            file formats can be used with Gwyddion. This means namely graphical file types (JPEG, PNG, PPM, TIFF, BMP) and raw binary
            and ASCII data. With <programlisting>io_tm</programlisting> plugin (distributed separately) you can load data from
            ThermoMicroscopes (Veeco) SpmLab #R4 and #R5 version binary files.
         </para>
         <para>
            We expect that much more file IO modules and plugins will be wrtiien soon, depending on demands and file format
            specifications available.
         </para>
       </section>
      <section>
         <title>Data windows</title>
         <para>
            Data window is used for 2D data presentation to user. It is the main widget used for working with Gwyddion.
            The data are presented to user as a field of false colors correponding to heights. Color axis that represents mapping
            the colors to real height values is also part of the data window. 
         </para>
         <para>
            Graph window is used for 1D data processing. You can get it only by using appropriate tools or modules that
            extract some graphs from height field data. Currently, it is not possible to load graphs into application as the main
            intent of Gwyddion is to provide tools for analyzing height fields, not graphs.
         </para>
        </section>
      <section>
         <title>Modules and tools</title>
         <para>
            Modules are responsible for most of the Gwyddion features.             
         </para>
         <para>
            Tools are a special kind of modules that can work with selections. 
         </para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Presentations and masks</title>
         <para>
            Presentations can be used to show the height field in other way than as false colors map of heights.
            Currently, only one presentation method - shading - is implemented.
         </para>
         <para>
            Masks are used for displaying special areal selections (e. g. grains).
         </para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Plugins</title>
         <para>
            Plugins are separate programmes that can communicate with gwyddion. From the point of user, the way of
            using plugins is same as for modules. From the point of developer, plugins are programmes that can load or
            save Gwyddion DUMB file format. They do not use any of Gwyddion libraries and therefore they are independent
            on Gwyddion licensing.
         </para>
      </section>
    </section>
   <section>
      <title>Developing Gwyddion</title>
      <para>
         You are encouraged to become a developer of Gwyddion.
      </para>
      <section>
         <title>API References</title>
         <para> 
            There are many functions that can help you while developing your module. Please, see API reference. 
         </para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Bug reports</title>
         <para>
            We will be very happy if you send as bug reports if you find errors in Gwyddion. For doing this,
            please, specify as much as possible the situation which leaded to error, operating system and
            Gwyddion version used. You can also send us the SPM data that were processed when problem was found,
            this is necessary namely for reporting bugs in file loading/saving modules and plugins.
         </para>
      </section>
    </section>
</book>

